Hey, hey. What's up, my friend? So, yep,
it's been a while and I hope you've
missed
me. So, today, right, we're going to
talk about the trading success formula
because here's the thing, right? 95% of
traders out there, they do not know what
it
takes to find trading success. They do
not have what it takes to be a
profitable
trader. That's why you have so many
traders blowing up their trading
accounts. That's why you have so many
traders going around in circles for
months, for
years without any results to show for.
That's why you have so many
traders who give up eventually because
they do not have a blueprint. They do
not know what it takes to find trading
success. So now the question is this,
what does it take for you to be a
consistently profitable trader to find
trading success?
Is it risk management,
psychology,
discipline?
No, it's not enough. And it goes much
more
deeper. And I know what you're thinking.
It's not what you're thinking as well.
Okay. So, I'll break all this down in
today's video. So, let's get started.
The first thing, NH. So, what is NH?
An h otherwise known as expectancy is
something that you do repeatedly that
yields a positive outcome. Let me give
you an
example. So let's say for example you
toss a coin and every time it comes up
head you win $2 and every time it comes
up tails you lose a dollar. Now let me
ask you in the long run will you make or
lose money? Well goes without saying
right you will make money in the long
run. Here's another example. So, say
this time around you toss a coin. But
this time around, every time it comes up
to heads, you win $1. And every time it
comes up tails, you lose $2. In the long
run, will you win or lose? And I'm sure
you'll say that you will lose in the
long run because your losses are larger
than your winners. So now the question
is this, how do you define an age? Let
me explain. Okay, so age can be defined
as this formula over here. Don't let it
scare you because you know it's not
difficult. Even a 12 year old can
understand this. So let me break this
down further for you. Okay. So E stands
for your
expectancy. Okay. If your E is positive,
we say that you have a positive
expectancy. Otherwise you have a
otherwise it means you have a positive
H. If your E is negative then you have a
negative expectancy. This winning
percentage refers to your winning rate
of your trading system. Your average
gain refers to you know how much do you
win on average? What is the average size
of your gains? What is the average size
of your winners? And then likewise, this
is your losing percentage. And then this
is the average size of your loss
whenever you take a losing trade or
whenever you take a loss. So let me give
you an example so you can see how this
works. So let's start with a example of
a positive age. So let's say you have a
trading system that wins 70% of the
time. Every time you win, right, you win
an average of, let's say, $80 $80. And
every time you lose, uh, you lose $100.
And needless to say, your losing rate is
30%. How you get 30%? You just take 100%
minus your winning rate, 70%, your
losing rate is 30%. Okay? So, let's say
your trading system has this matrix. So,
what is your expectancy? Just plug in
this number right into the formula and
you will get, let me just walk you
through an example, right? So your E is
equals to 0.7 which is your winning rate
multiply by $80 which is the average
gain right of your winners on average
plus your sorry
minus your losing rate which is 30% 0.3
multiply by the average size of your
losses which is 100. Okay. So, just plug
this in, right? I mean, you don't need
to use a calculator. So, this first
figure will be 56 minus 30 and you get
$26. So, what does this $26 means? This
$26 means
that on average, right, after a series
of trade, you can expect to make an
average of about $26 per trade. So this
means let's say you take a 100 trades.
How much do you expect your account to
be up to be increased after 100 trades?
You can expect your account to be up 26
multiply by 100 trades $2,600. So this
is the beauty, right, of being able to
define your age, your expectancy. Now
this is an example of a positive age.
But here's the thing, right? Not all
trading systems have a positive age. So
let me give you an example this time
around of a negative age. Again, we go
with a 70% winning rate, but this time
around, the average size of your gains
is $10. Losing rate is 30% and the
average size of your loss is $100. So,
this time around, what is your
expectancy? So, again, using the same
formula I shared with you, your
expectancy this time around will be -23.
What does this means? This means, right,
that on average, every time you put on
the trade, you can expect to lose $23 on
average. Okay. Okay. Now, as you can see
right in this case, even though you have
a 70% winning rate, you have a negative
expectancy. But previously in example
three, you also have a 70% winning rate,
but you have a positive expectancy. Why
is that? What's the difference? Well,
the difference here
is the size of your average gains
relative to your average loss. Some
people call this the risk-to-reward
ratio. Yeah, very similar concept. So,
that is the difference, right? Because
in example three, your average gain is
$80. Whereas in example four, your
average gain is only $10. So this means
that your gains is much smaller than
your average loss. And that's why you
have a negative
expectancy. Now you might be thinking,
so Raina, does it mean that you know
your average gains to your average loss
is the most important thing? Does it
mean that I need to look for a minimum
of a 1:2 riskreward ratio? Hm. Let's
find out. Let's say you have a 1:2
risk-reward ratio. Okay? Let's say your
average gain is twice the size of of
your loss. So let's say you have a
minimum of a 1 to2 reward ratio. Let's
call it your RR risk to reward ratio.
Let's say over 10 trades. 1 2 3 4 5 6 7
8 9 10. Over 10 trades you have, let's
say a 20% winning rate. Okay? Let's say
your first two trades are winners. And
let's say you risk a dollar on each
trade. So if you have a 1 to2 riskreward
ratio on the trade means you make two
times what you risk. So the first two
trades are winner and winner and the
remaining eight trades let's say they
are losses right so min -1 -1 -1 -1 -1
-1 -1 - one you get the point so you sum
up everything what is your net return
well your net return is -4 negative four
this means you have lost money after
making 10 trades in other words even
though you have a favorable
risk-to-reward ratio of a 1 to2
riskreward ratio you still have a
negative ative expectancy. Yeah. So
what's the point that I'm trying to
make? It is this right? This is
something that many traders are just
unaware of. It is this on its own. Your
winning rate or risk-to-reward ratio is
meaningless. Okay? You need to combine
both both of them to know whether your
trading system has an edge or not. You
can't just focus on one. You can't just
focus on your winning rate. You can't
just look at the riskto-reward ratio
because on its own each of these matrix
are meaningless. You need to combine
both. Only both of them will you know
whether you have an age or whether you
have a positive
expectancy. Make sense? So it's kind of
like you know finding a girl right maybe
for girlfriend or for marriage material.
You can't just
look at what what's outside of the girl
you know how pretty her face is because
her inside could be horrendous right?
When you want to find a partner to marry
you need to both look at the inside and
the outside of the girl. Just like you
must have both your winning rate and
your risk-to-reward ratio. Right? Both
of them when you combine together only
then will you make a more educated
decision to whether you want to marry
that girl or whether you want to take
that system that has an age in the
markets or not. Now here's the thing
right having an age itself is not
enough. Okay I repeat it's not enough
because you also
need risk management. So let me explain.
So risk risk management protects your
downside no matter what happens even if
you have 10 losing trades in a row.
That's the power of risk management
because without it, without risk
management, even a profitable trading
system, even the best trading system
that you know of will fail. Let me give
you an example to see how this works. So
imagine this. Imagine there are two
traders, John and Sally, because that's
kind of like the most universal name I
can think of. All right, let's say they
both have a $10,000 trading account, and
they have a 50% winning rate. They have
an average of a 1:2 riskreward ratio. So
let's say every time they risk a dollar,
if they are wrong, they lose $1. If they
are right, they make $3. So three times
the amount that they risk. John risk
$5,000 per trade and Sally risk $100 per
trade. Now let's say the outcome of the
next 10 trades is as follows, right? You
know, lose, lose, lose, lose, lose, and
then followed by wins. What do you think
is the result of both traders after
these 10 trades? So let's find out. So
let's talk about John first, right?
John. So John, right, is a trader that,
you know, either, you know, goes big or
goes home. So first two trades are
losses. So he minus
$5,000 and then minus
$5,000. So as you can tell, John would
have, you know, gone belly up, blown up,
right, his account after two trades.
Now, what about Sally? Okay, Sally. So
Sally is more conservative. She only
risked $100 per trade. So just let's say
- 100 - 100 - 100 - 100 and then - 100
because the first five trades over here
1 2 3 4 5 are losing trades but then
because she has sound risk management
see she survived to see the better days
ahead so the next five trades are
winners okay so since it's a average of
a 1 to2 risk-reward ratio her gains are
like plus
300 plus
300 300 I'm just going to just 300 and
300. Okay. So what's her net profit
after these 10 trades? So her total loss
over here is negative 500, right? 1 2 3
4 5 and her total gains is here is,5.
So,5 I just put minus 500
plus,05. You can see that just making
sure my calculation is correct because
you'll be embarrassed right if you can't
do this simple math right in front of
public. All right, and then posting this
video on YouTube only to get the math
wrong. I don't know where to hide my
face. 369 1215. All right. So, net gain
of
$1,000. Okay. So, in other words, Sally
has made a net profit of $1,000 after 10
trades. A 10% gain on her account,
whereas John has blown up. And this is
where things
get interesting. Both of them, right,
let me just remove all the drawings.
Both of them has a same size trading
account, same trading system. The only
difference is the amount that they risk
per trade. One end up blowing up his
account and one made a gain of 10%. So
can you see how important risk
management is
because without it right you
know you are given the best trading
system in the world you will still lose
in the long run because of a lack of
proper risk management. Let's say you
have proper risk management. Let's say
you have a positive expectancy. Does it
mean that you're ready to become a
profitable trader? Not quite. Because
you still need this third thing,
discipline. Discipline refers to
following the rules of your trading
system. No matter what happens, even if
you're on a holiday, even if you don't
feel like it, even after 10 losing
trades in a row, guess what? You still
must follow the rules of your trading
system. When the setup presents itself,
when the opportunity presents itself,
you must take it. Yeah. Because what
happens if you don't, right, is because
if you start skipping trades based on
how you feel, based on maybe your
emotions, then you end up skipping
trades. And let's say the next trade
that you're supposed to take, you end up
skipping it. That could be a winner, a
winning trade that could pay for all the
little losses that you have incurred
previously. But by skipping it, guess
what? You don't have the chance to
recover from your losses. You're still
in the red because you end up skipping
your trades. So to kind of kind of
illustrate this point, right? Imagine
this. Imagine the outcome of your next
seven trades are as follows. Okay, you
have three losing
trades, one, two, three losses and then
followed by four winners. Okay, let's
say at this point, right, you have just
taken three losses in a row. At this
point over here, you have taken three
losses in a row. What is your thought
process going to be? I think for many
traders, their top process is along the
lines of let's say uh the fourth trading
opportunity appears. They are thinking,
man, I've just had three losses in a
row, man. you know this trade this
fourth trade this fourth opportunity is
probably going to be a loser let me skip
this trade so they skip the trade and
what happens that fourth trade happened
to be a winner now at the fifth trading
opportunity they're faced with this
choice again hm should I take this trade
or not but you know look at it as a
whole right you know over the last four
trades right three of them are losses
man the losses the pain is still there
ah emotions is still raw you know what I
want to play it safe let's be more
conservative. Let's play it safe. Let's
skip this trade. And then guess what?
The fifth trade is a winner which they
miss once again. Yeah. And now they
presented with this six trading
opportunity and then they look at it,
they're in a really tough spot, a
dilemma, you know, man, should I take
this trade? You know, the three losses,
it sucks. But guess what? I missed the
opportunity of the recent two winning
trades. I think right now you know the
market is about to to turn right. I
think right now the system right is
about to go into a draw down right after
all we have two recent winners. This
next third trade or rather this next six
trade is likely to be a loser right
since you know the tide is changing let
me skip this trade as well and then
guess what it's a winning trade at this
point you ah you can't take it anymore.
Yeah, if you had followed the rules of
your trading system, right, you would
have, you know, been in a much better
shape. But because you you doubted
yourself, you're
emotional. You didn't dare to click the
button even though you're supposed to do
it. But right now, you have no choice.
You tell yourself, I will follow the
rule no matter what. I must follow the
rules of my trading system because Raina
say so. So the seven trading
opportunity, you finally decide to take
the trade and
finally you capture this winner.
Okay. But because your fourth, fifth,
and sixth trade you didn't take and you
only took the seven trade which is a
winner, that win right is not enough to
pay for your earlier three losses and
overall you're still down on your
trading account. And this is what
happens when you don't have the
discipline to follow your rules. When
you start cherrypicking trades to
take, when you start to doubt yourself,
when you start to doubt the trading
system, this is what happens. Yeah. So,
discipline, right? This is the third
ingredient, right, that you need to be a
successful, profitable trader. Okay.
Here's a tip for you. Or rather, here is
something that you must know. Consistent
action leads to consistent results.
If you want to be a consistently
profitable trader, then you must be
consistent with your actions. Because
think about this, if your actions are
inconsistent, then clearly your results
will be inconsistent. So the way to be
consistent with your actions is to be a
disciplined trader. And if you struggle
with discipline, don't worry. Later on,
I have I have a tip for you. But for
now, let's move on and talk about this.
Why do most traders fail? And how can
you avoid it? So there are few reasons
why most traders fail. And let me break
it down to you. Number one, no risk
management and what to do about it. So
if you are the type of
traders trader that has blown up
multiple trading account or whenever you
have a losing trade, your losses is like
40 50 60% the size of your account. This
means that you clearly don't have proper
risk management or you do not know how
to calculate the optimal position
size for the size of your account. Don't
worry, right? Because uh I'm not going
to go through a risk management training
in this video here. But in the
description below this video, I will put
trainings on how to master risk
management. Whether you're trading the
forex market, whether you're trading the
stock markets, I will put uh videos,
video tutorials in the description. Just
check out the link below and it will
benefit you. And the good news is this,
risk management isn't difficult. Just
give me 30, 40 minutes of your time, you
will be able to master risk management.
And this is a tool that will pay
dividends for the rest of your trading
career. Because guess what? Whether you
are trading on your first day of your
trading career or the last day on your
trading of your trading career, risk
management will be there every step of
the way. You need risk management no
matter what. Doesn't mean that you are a
veteran trader who've been trading for
50 years. You can ignore risk
management. No, it still is as essential
right as day one. So don't neglect risk
management and the tutorial will be in
the description
below. Reason number two, you don't have
an age in the market and what can you do
about it? So this scenario is for those
of you who understand risk management
but still you suffer losses quite a few
losses and these losses right even
though they're not huge they are
starting to eat into
your trading account right you're
suffering what I call death by a
thousand cards you're not getting killed
by one or two trades but 20 30 losing
trades right I won't say in a row but
you know in total right and your winners
are not enough to pay for your losses
this slowly eat into your trade trading
account. So this is what I call death by
a thousand card. So what can you do
about this? Well, the problem with this
is that you probably don't have an age
in the market. So even though you have
proper risk management, your trading
system, right, likely isn't working.
It's something that's not proven to work
in the market. So you need to get an H
in the market. So this is where you need
to do things like, you know, uh testing
of trading system, back testing, forward
testing, etc. And to make your life
easier, you can grab a copy of my this
new book called Trading Systems that
work. I will equip you with three proven
trading systems that work not just based
on theory. It's backed by quantifiable
data. You can use these three different
trading systems to as a foundation to
build your own trading system or you
want to copy it for your own trading. I
leave it to you. And number three, this
one, no discipline. Right? If you are
the trader that lacks discipline, you
know what you should do. You know proper
risk management, but you have to
struggle following the rules of your
trading system, then this is what I I
recommend. Right? One technique I find
particularly effective is to find an
accountability partner. Someone that
you're accountable to. This could be
your spouse, your trading buddy or
whoever that you trust. And it goes
something like this, right? How does it
work? So you will have that someone that
accountability partner check in on you
every week to check whether you have
followed the rules of your trading
system. And you got to be honest, right?
Yes, I I did follow the rules this week.
No, I messed up this week. So that
partner will check in with you every
single week. And then if let's say you
didn't follow the rules of that week,
you will then be penalized getting a
punishment. The punishment could be
something like treating your
accountability partner to a meal, making
$50 or $100 to a charity, something that
is painful, right? So the pain has to
stink a little bit such that in future
when you think of, you know, not
following the rules of your trading
system or not being disciplined, you'll
be reminded of that that pain, right?
The pain of, you know, getting penalized
or getting punished. So this right will
then help you become a more disciplined
trader to follow the rules of your
trading system. So I find that having
this accountability partner really
useful. Okay. To sum up right, the
trading success formula is as
follows. It's this trading success
is having a trading system that has an
edge in the markets. You having sound
risk management so you don't blow up
your trading account. And having the
discipline to follow the rules of your
trading system no matter what happens.
Whether you're feeling sick, you're on a
holiday, whatsoever. This is the trading
success formula. And you can't do or
rather you can't have one without the
others. For example, you can't say, "Oh,
Raina, what if I only have risk
management and discipline, but I don't
have an H?" Then guess what? You'll
suffer death by a thousand cuts. Or what
if you know someone says, "Rain, what if
I only have an H in markets, but I lack
risk management? I lack discipline." And
guess what? You will blow up multiple
trading account. So this is why this is
not a buffet where you can pick and
choose what you like to eat like the
chicken wings, the cream brulee. No, you
got to have all three components. I
repeat, you have got to have all three
components if you want to be a
successful trader. There is no qualms
about it. You can't, you know, argue
about it. You need these three
components. And in this video, right, I
have shared insights on how you can
achieve, right, or master these three
components.
Now you might be wondering so Rain you
know which of these three should I work
on first I'm a new trader you know six
years or rather six months trading
experience here's my opinion if you're
new to trading right work on your risk
management first
why that's because risk management is
the lowest hanging fruit right that you
can tackle as a trader all you need is
about 45 minutes of your time to learn
the math behind risk management and
position sizing the math is not
difficult a 12-year-old will be able to
understand it and you will be able to
master risk management. And the
importance of risk management is since
the first day of trading till the last
day of trading till the day you decide
to retire. Risk management right has to
be in place since the day you start
trading till the end of your retirement.
And it's not difficult to master. 45
minutes is all you need. And I will put
a training a risk management training in
the description below of this video if
you need help on it. Once you master
risk management, which isn't going to
take long, that's where you need to find
your edge in the markets. And if you ask
me, based on my experience, that's the
hardest part about trading. Finding a
trading system that works, finding an
edge in the markets, right? I spent
years looking for this. And this is why
I write the book, right? Trading systems
that work to help shortcut your learning
curve. Because it's after years of trial
and error, experimenting, testing, I
kind of realized, hey, you know, this
few trading systems, right, are likely
to work for the foreseeable future. And
again, if you want to shortcut your
learning curve, you can grab the book,
right? Trading system that that work.
And then finally, discipline. Why I put
discipline last is because once you have
sound risk management, once you have an
age in the markets, your discipline will
simply be a byproduct of it. Right? Why
why do people have discipline problems?
Why do they have difficulty following
the rules? Well, it's because they don't
have conviction in their trading system.
They do not know whether it works or
not. Is it something wrong with the
system or is it me? you know all these
doubts and and and and struggles in them
that's why they have or rather they
struggle with discipline in following
their rules. So once you settle your
risk management once you have an edge in
the markets discipline usually naturally
follows along with it and that's why I
kind of put it last and of course if if
you still struggle with discipline
that's where I spoke about earlier you
know finding an accountability partner
right to help you with whatever
discipline issues you might have. So to
recap, number one, trading success is
when you have an H, proper risk
management, and the discipline to follow
your rules. That is
the trading success formula. And why
most traders fail is because they lack
one of these components in their
trading. But when you have all three,
you are unstoppable, baby. And by the
way, if you want to grab a copy of the
book, Trading Systems that work, you can
just go down to this website over here.
The link over here is uh trading
systemsbook.com. I wish it's called
trading systems uh that work but that
domain is taken up. So trading
systemsbook.com I'll put the link in the
description as well. You can grab a copy
of this book uh for just at this price
point is now 17 bucks and it comes along
with uh a few bonuses, right? But I
think what's what's really interesting
is that this is not just a book about
one trading system, right? It has three
three different trading system, right?
First you have the trend following
system, you have the mean reversion
trading system and the breakout trading
system. and the exact trading rules, the
back test results are all in the book,
right? I don't hide any of the rules or
whatsoever from you. So, all these three
trading systems, they are quantifiable.
They've been tested, right? And proven
to work, right? Uh for the foreseeable
future. So, again, I'll put the link
somewhere below this book. Grab a copy
and for whatever reason, you know, if
you're not happy, right, uh just let me
know, right? Within the first 180 days,
I give you a full 180 days to kind of
like test this uh this uh this book, the
concepts, the systems. If you're not
happy, just email me, right? And I'll
happily refund you info, right? No
questions asked again. So, I'll put the
link below this video. Grab a copy. And
with that, I wish you good luck, good
trading, and I will talk to you soon.